I would like to know the wise ways
to resolve the conflicts among friends.
I came to ask you about issues regarding
the interpersonal relationships.
In general, I don't have strong opinions
and I tend to be easy going.
So, I am able to understand and accept
other people's opinions for the most part.
And when I am around an opinionated
person, I tend to go along with him..
So, when it comes to
the conflicts among friends,
for example, if friends A and B
are in conflict and are arguing,
listening to A, I can understand A while
listening to B, I can also understand B.
Since they are not able to
understand each other,
I end up listening to
both badmouthing each other.
Since I am not sure about how to
handle such situations, I ask other people
I am told that I should side with
whomever I am talking to at the time.
But I feel that would be like
playing one against the other.
I also feel that I am being fraudulent
when I don't mean to be.
When I have to mediate in such situations,
what is the wise way to
handle the conflicts?
(Sunim) You should not do anything.
Got it? You just do nothing.
Taking sides of one or the other seems
like you're coming between them, right?
So, you just do nothing.
Then, where is the problem?
(Questioner)
Yes, it seems like I should do nothing.
(Sunim)
See how easy it is.
Then, why are you wracking
your brain worrying about this?
You do that because you are
overestimating yourself.
Since you are not capable to help,
you ought to do nothing.
What does it mean to do nothing?
When your friends say something,
you ought to listen to them, right?
(Questioner)
Yes, I should listen.
Right. So, when this one says such and such,
you just say, "Right, yes, I see."
You just listen and say,
"Yes, yes, is that right?"
If you say, "He was wrong,"
you would be taking sides. You see?
No matter how badly A speaks of B,
you cannot speak ill of B.
Also, you shouldn't tell A that he is
wrong or tell him to understand B.
Then, A will be upset.
If you take A's side and criticize B,
A may feel happy,
but later when B hears about it,
he will be upset or no?
(Questioner)
Yes, he will be upset.
(Sunim)
Then, that is coming between them.
So, just listen to them.
By the same token,
if you say that you don't want to
get involved in their skirmish,
then, you are not being
a good friend to them.
Do you understand
what I am trying to say?
(Questioner)
Yes.
(Sunim)
So, what to do? Just listen.
Just listen
but don't try to solve their problems
Just say,
"Yes, yes, I know. I see. Is that right?"
"That must have been tough for you."
And when B tells his version
of the story, again you say,
" Oh, yes. I see. Sure sounds rough."
If you handle like this, you have
criticized neither A nor B, right?
(Questioner)
Yes.
(Sunim)
You have not taken sides, have you?
(Questioner)
No.
(Sunim)
You have listened to them or not?
(Questioner)
I have.
(Sunim) You have listened to them
as a friend but have not taken sides.
You only need to listen to them.
They have become so upset
that they had to tell somebody.
So, you listen to them
but do not try to solve the problem.
Trying to solve their problem means that
you are interfering in their lives.
You don't have the ability to do that yet.
I don't have the ability to do
that sort of thing yet either.
So, just listen to them.
Counseling is 90% listening.
It is not about solving problems.
It seems as though
I solve your problems, right?
You are mistaken if you think so.
I have never solved any problem.
I just ask questions regarding
this and that, and I listen.
Then the questioners
find solutions themselves.
I get all the credit
even though it's the questioners
themselves who find the solutions.
(Audience Laughter)
Since it's not a bad thing,
I just let it be.
(Audience Laughter)
So, without telling you what to do,
if I just tell you,
"It's not a big deal." then you, too,
realize that it's not a big deal, right?
(Questioner)
Yes.
(Sunim)
So, did I solve anything for you?
(Questioner)
um..
(Sunim) You came to realize that
it's not a big deal.
So. all you have to do
also is to just listen.
Then, there is no problem whatsoever.
How cool is it?
You can get along well with A and B.
If and when your parents fight,
if your mom says something,
you just reply, "Yes, yes, I see."
When your dad says something,
just say, "Yes, yes, I see."
Why? Why do you need to get
involved in a couple's fighting?
Understand?
(Questioner)
Yes.
If you take your mom's side
and blame your dad,
you'd become a bad child to your father.
Likewise, if you side with your dad,
you'd be a bad child to your mom.
You end up being the bad guy without
having resolved anything for them.
So, you just listen to
their woes as their son.
Understand?
You cannot solve the problem.
How can you solve the problem
between them?
They, themselves,
are not able to resolve them.
So, you just listen to them.
By doing nothing, I mean that you do not
try to solve their problems.
Just by being listened to,
they'd be able to solve their problems.
Just as I listen to
the questioner's problem,
the questioner finds the solution.
For example, who would feel better
if the wife, instead of hating the husband
decides to understand the husband?
Will the husband feel better?
Sometimes,
People think that I side with husbands.
Why would I take the husbands' sides?
Why would I take anybody's side?
For what reason
would I side with anybody?
Audience: Because you are a man, too!
(Audience Laughter)
Yes, I know that some people say that.
But, let's look at it closely.
Why am I more popular among women
even though I always side with men?
What's going on here?
Have you read the article
from a women's organization criticizing me
as an influential monk
who always takes men's sides
by admonishing women to yield to men?
There was an article of
multiple pages criticizing me.
Well, I guess they could think that way.
What's to be done about it?
What else is there to do?
The best thing is
not to be living together.
If I say not to live together,
I am told it's because I live alone.
I am telling them
to live alone as I do, they say.
So, if you are going to live together,
is it better to live
with conflict or without conflicts?
Right. If you want to live
without conflict, you need to do that.
If I side with husbands, will the wives
change or the husbands change?
If I take the wives' sides,
will the husbands change?
Without ever having met, how can
he change because I take his sides?
But I am always
on the side of the questioner.
What does that mean?
I give advice for
the benefit of the questioner,
without regard to who is right or wrong.
For the benefit of the questioner.
So, only listen to the people
who seek the counsel.
Do not try to solve their problems.
You can't solve their problems.
In life, we all have to solve
our own problems by ourselves.
Nobody can do it for us.
The reason people thank me
for the little advice I give them,
is due to the fact that they themselves come to
an understanding and get enlightened.
If it's true that
I solve problems for them,
I should be able to solve
everyone's problem.
If I solved one person's problem,
I would not be able to solve
the other's problem.
Why should I be taking on
other people's problems?
The reason I say that I had done nothing
when I am thanked,
is my way of defending myself against
those whose problems remain.
Everyone needs to live
according to one's own way.
A third party cannot solve
anyone's problem.
Not even your parents, nor siblings.
So, listening is an expression
of your friendship and courtesy.
Not taking sides nor
solving problems for them.
(Applause)